Hello and welcome back to another video
with ItsDrDan, and today we're going to
be looking at the hydrolysis of esters
for introductory organic chemistry.
So what is that all about?
Well, try to think of the word, right?
Hydro.
If you think of hydro, what's the
first thing that comes to your mind?
Well, hopefully it is water, right?
So whenever we have hydro, the
entire idea should be water.
Now, When we look at the rest of the
word, lysis, well, if you're someone that
maybe has taken physiology or microbiology
or any type of intro to bio, lysis is
all about destroying or getting rid of,
well, lysis in particular stands for to
cut, so what we are going to be doing
is we're going to be cutting with water.
So instead, if you remember
from esterification videos, that
was all about removing water.
Hydrolysis is the opposite
process where this time we're
going to be cutting with water.
Now, depending on how we can cut
with water, this is something that
can exist in two different ways.
Now, so we have acid catalyzed hydrolysis.
And then we also have base
catalyzed hydrolysis, also known as
saponification, so, which is making soap.
So, we're going to be diving into
both of those different reactions
in this video, starting with acid
catalyzed, going through trying
to understand that, and then going
through many examples along the way.
Acid hydrolysis is when water reacts
with an ester in the presence of a
strong acid like HCl, H2SO4, or or HNO3.
And when it does that, it's going to
make it into the original components that
made the ester in the first place, which
is an alcohol and a carboxylic acid.
So as I mentioned earlier, this
is the opposite of esterification.
So with this, we're going
to be cutting our bond.
So when we are looking at this, well, how
exactly are we going to be cutting it?
What are the different parts of this?
Well, it's going to be similar to a
lot of reactions that we had before,
especially if you think of hydration
reactions back during addition.
Now with a hydration.
The big thing is here is that you were
adding an -H and an -OH component to this.
And it's gonna be very similar here.
'cause the whole goal is to
get our original components.
So when I cut this particular
bond, right, so if I put my little
scissors here and we cut this, we're
going to be adding our two parts.
Now keep in mind what is our
goal is we want an alcohol.
and a carboxylic acid.
So the first one is if I want an alcohol,
well the most likely candidate for that
is going to be the part on the right,
and it's going to be putting our little
puzzle piece of an H attached to that.
So if I add my part here where I
have an H connected to O R, Right,
we have an alcohol that is formed.
Now on the other part, well, for our OH,
that's going to make our carboxylic acid.
So when we put all those pieces back
together, we have our R C O, double,
our C double bond O, with an OH
component, which are our two pieces
from our water molecule put together.
So we have alcohol and then a carboxylic
acid As our two components here and that's
the general idea is that whenever we have
an acid with heat We can cut the bond and
completely change what it is before right?
So when this happens the pH is going to
change Because now you have an acid as
one of your properties So you should see
results and a change in how it behaves
and how it smells too Okay, let's go
through some different examples of this.
Alright, our first type of example.
So here what we're going to be doing
is predicting the following reaction.
Meaning we're going to go through
hydrolysis by adding an acid to
the following different compounds.
So commonly the way that you will see
an acid introduced is whenever you
have an H plus written, because if
you think of an acid, it's something
that donates a proton in a reaction.
And if acids and bases are something
that aren't as memorable, go over
to my acids and bases video and then
I'll help you remember that concept.
So, with this one, right, the whole
idea is that we have this ester and
we're going to be cutting it with water.
So when we are cutting this, we do
it between the carbon and the O,
so it's between the two different
parts of the functional group here.
So when we cut, right, we're
going to be adding H and OH
to our two different pieces.
making a carboxylic acid and an alcohol.
Now the portion that is the ether
side, right, so if I were to
kind of label these, the ether is
going to go towards the alcohol.
And the more, the C double bond O is
going to turn into a carboxylic acid.
If you were to kind of break apart the
ester into what components does it have.
So the carbonyl will
feed the carboxylic acid.
When we do that, we are going to
be, we are going to take our C
double bond O, that will have our OH
component to make the carboxylic acid.
And then on the other part, the
alcohol is going to be our HO with
our 2 propanol on the other structure.
So then we have the two different
products that you're going to have and
you have to list out all the products
that are being made in these reactions.
Or you did not predict the
products correctly, right?
You have to list them all.
Now on the next one, it's going to
be the same general idea, right?
We're going to cut our bond.
right between the two oxygens.
Now we're going to add
our two components, right?
So we have H and OH are
what's going to be added here.
So we're going to redraw our carbons,
which that's another thing to mention as
you're going through these, make sure you
still have all of your carbons accounted
for at the end of the reaction, right?
So in this particular one, we have eight
carbons going in, we should have eight
coming out of it in the end as well.
So make sure you check, right?
So you have the benzene ring,
which is six, the C double bond
O, which makes a seventh carbon.
Then we will add our OH to this.
And then on our other part, we have a
methanol, which is our eighth carbon.
So you can see that everything is
accounted for in this reaction.
So we, this is your acid
base catalyzed reactions.
Let's go on to our base
hydrolysis type reactions.
Okay.
Now we're going to be
looking at saponification.
also known as base hydrolysis, which
is really similar to the concept of
actually making soap or how soap works.
Um, so with this one, we're going
to see when an ester is going to
undergo hydrolysis, but this is
in the presence of a strong base.
Um, Mark particularly might see
sodium hydroxide, which is NaOH or
potentially potassium hydroxide.
which is KOH now the products for this
are a carboxylate salt which we'll go
over what that show it looks like and an
alcohol so with this particular reaction
I'm going to try to explain it in like
the I would think it's like the easier
way just to kind of memorize it for
yourself and how the reaction happens
not the exact actual like mechanism
behind it because it's a little more
complicated than the acid hydrolysis.
But if you think of it in terms
of trading charges, it actually
will make a little bit more sense
if you remember it this way.
So what exactly is it?
So let's take a look.
So when we have, let's say an Esther
with a base, so we have the Esther on the
left hand side, uh, which is right here.
And then we have our strong base.
Now remember this whole entire
thing, it's going to be under heat
and involving water because that's,
what's going to be doing the cutting.
Now for this one, the easiest
way to think about it is let's
look more at the charges here.
Um, and I know these are not
ionic, entirely ionic species,
but it's something that it makes
them make a little bit more sense.
So if you have the first one, which let's
say if we look at the sodium hydroxide,
right, we have a plus and then we have a
minus on the two portions of that, right?
Because it's an ionic species.
Now, the whole idea here is that
we want to trade positives, okay,
so that's what we're going to say.
Trade positives, because we always
like being positive around here, right?
So when we are being positive,
we want to trade positivity.
So how can we label that on our ester?
Well, if you remember from
hydrolysis, the main part of
hydrolysis is going to be happening
right kind of around this oxygen.
In particular, this one's going to be
more on the right hand side for this
particular one, just so it makes sense.
We're going to trade positives.
So it, what is negative in this case?
Is it the oxygen or
would it be the R group?
Well, if you think of.
oxygen.
It's on that top right hand
side of the periodic table.
So it's more electronegative.
So I'm going to label
that with a negative.
Now with the R group, this
is going to be R positive.
We're going to trade the two positives.
Okay.
So we're going to do a little
bit of a swappy, swappy.
and trade the two
different portions, right?
So kind of like a double
replacement reaction.
So when that happens, now we are going
to be making on the left hand side of
this reaction is our carboxylate salt.
Now, why is it referred
to as a carboxylate salt?
Well, if you think of a salt
compound, that is whenever
we have ionic charges, okay?
So we need to make sure
that we do illustrate the
ionic charge when it comes to the product.
You must write the charges.
So when we treated them, this made a Na
plus salt, which is going to change the
solubility of this compound immensely.
The second you add that ionic
characteristic, ion dipole forces
are possible, which is the strongest
intermolecular force that you can have.
So, this is stuff that makes
like fats and oils soluble if
you think of in the sink, right?
If you mix it with, let's say, if you
are washing a pan after cooking and
it has oil on it and you wash it with
only water, does the oil come off?
And the answer is no, obviously not.
What do you do?
You add soap.
Well, soap is what's going to make
it have an ionic charge and make it
very similar to this, causing it to
be soluble and immiscible in water and
cause it to go down the drain, right?
So it's a very similar idea here.
So we'll also make an
alcohol component as well.
So alcohol in that carboxylic
salt is the two different pieces.
Let's go through trying to
practice the idea of trading
positives to make our products.
And if this is something that
you want to try it on your own,
fully I recommend pausing it.
We're going to go through two examples
of how to look at these reactions.
All right, let's do an example
of base hydrolysis with an
actual chemical compound.
Now with this one, you can see that we
have an ester compound on the left hand
side, and it's being added to sodium
hydroxide, and this is under heat.
Now the question you might think of
is, oh, I thought this was hydrolysis.
Where's the water?
Well, remember, sodium hydroxide,
or an acid or a base, is made in
water, so it's always assumed that
this is aqueous, and that there
is water present in the reaction.
So same idea here is we are going to
be treating our positive components.
So, trading positives, well, let's label
our charges to help remember, right?
Sodium is a plus, hydroxide
is a minus charge.
Same idea here is we're going to label
our oxygen and then we'll label our
carbonyl portion with a positive.
Now, when we are doing that, right,
we are cutting our two charges apart,
and we can even draw scissors even
on the sodium hydroxide to help
show that, right, we're cutting both
these pieces, and we are trading them
as in the, as a result, right, so
trade, let's even draw some arrows.
So it never hurts to draw a bunch
of arrows, we're making a trade.
Now, when that happens, We are going
to redraw our carbon chain, right?
So we have a CO double bond O.
We have our oxygen, right?
And remember this has a minus charge
next to it, and we are trading it with
the sodium, which also has a positive.
Now keep in mind, this
is a carboxylic salt.
So we need to make sure
we realize that is a salt.
Now to make that even
more specific, right?
So the carboxylic salt You can
go through and try to name it,
too, if you ever needed to.
So, for example, this would
have been acetic acid if it
was an H instead of an Na.
In this case, it's sodium
acetate is our specific chemical.
So, sodium acetate.
So, sodium for the metal and carbons.
Now you can also name it sodium,
um, I guess you do ethanate.
Yeah, that sounds a little weird I don't
think I've ever heard it not acetate.
So maybe just sodium acetate
would be fine for the salt.
Now Is that the only thing?
Well, we missed a part
of our molecule, right?
We had to trade the other portion as
well So we have our two carbons attached
to an alcohol would be your other part.
So we also would have ethanol
made in our reaction, right?
So ethanol and then a carboxylic salt.
Specifically, sodium acetate.
This is how you can do this reaction.
Let's do one more.
Okay, let's predict the product
of the following reaction.
So let's do a question.
So if I have the following ester,
how do we go through base hydrolysis?
Well, like I said before, we're going
to do a little bit of a swappy swappy
and trade our two different charges.
So let's go through and
label them for ourselves.
So the first thing we're going
to do is we're going to label the
sodium, label the hydroxide, right?
So our plus and minus.
Then we're going to do the same
thing on our ester as well, right?
So the, the oxygen is a minus.
The part portion of the ether
outside is going to be our positive.
We're going to trade the two
positive components, okay?
So we're going to go through that trade.
So after we do the trade,
we're going to be making two
completely different components.
So we're going to bring it back over
the, um, the benzene ring here, right?
So just like this.
Then we will put in our O, our C
double bond O, as well as, and I'm
going to just kind of emphasize
that O minus with an Na plus, right?
So that's what makes our salt compound.
Now the other portion is
going to be an alcohol.
So we'll have our h o attached to
being that this is a one member
chain, so it'd be the H three
oh or also known as methanol.
So we have our two individual
components of our reaction.
So we'll make methanol
and a carboxyl salt.
I hope that this video helped.
So this is the whole idea of how to do
base hydrolysis and acid hydrolysis.
Kind of looking at both of them, right?
So base hydrolysis
makes the salt compound.
When it comes to acid hydrolysis,
it goes back to the original
components of the reaction, which
is a carboxylic acid and an alcohol.
The one good thing about remembering
is that they both make alcohols.
It's just whether or not
they make a salt or not.
Usually the way I always remember it
personally is that if I have, let's
say, sodium here, We can see that a
metal is involved or something that
is on those alkali metals, right?
So when you see that, that hopefully
will raise that flag, like, Oh, I need
to make sure I include that in the
product versus when you had HCl, for
example, as an acid, there's nowhere
for that, for that chlorine to go.
So the sodium attached to the
positive portion is always attaching.
So I hope that this video helped.
Please feel free to like, and subscribe
and to come by for future videos.
There will be much more coming out
for organic chemistry as well as
introductory organic chemistry.
And this has been Dr.
Dan.
Please let me know what you thought
and if there's anything else you'd
like to see in future videos.
Bye now!